Hello, everyone
I'd like to welcome you all to this
Fall's this term's instance of this course is officially either 15 to 13 from computer science
Or 18 to 13 from electrical and computer engineering
but a large number the people enrolled in this course are in one called 513 which is for graduate students and
To be totally honest you're not supposed to be here because you're supposed to watch the videos
The lectures by video later, but we're not checking any card, so I don't really know who you are. Oh
Anyways, this course is as you can see a very popular course on campus we have over 700 700
600 shouldn't exaggerate
students on campus enrolled in one of those three versions of the course
Which if you think about a university of the size of CMU that's like?
about five percent of the total
student population
So we're very glad to
Have you here and this game is too high I?
Think we overdid the game
Try that that's better um
so my name is Randy Bryant and
My co-instructor is Dave. O'halloran and those names might be familiar if you have been to the bookstore
Because the book was written by us, and we actually wrote this book
We started to 13 as a course in
1998 ah
and I know that your children then and all that stuff but
out of response for a new type of course that you'll see today that sort of gives people a
In-depth understanding of systems, but more from a high-level or programmers perspective
And we'll talk some about the philosophy of the course later
So this book has used as you see just came out its third edition
Last March
And that's the required text for the course and there is nothing you can do
To avoid buying that book and it's not because we're greedy
Actually, we take the money we get from royalty for students in this course or any CMU course and we donate it to CMU
So we're not actually making any money out of you buying the book, but it's a simple reality that the new version is
Different than the old we expect you to be using the new version. There are no electronic copies. There are no
pirated versions, so you basically have to buy the book but and
I don't really apologize to that because I
Know you or your parents do somebody's paying
a lot of money for you to be here and so the price of the book is really a
relatively small amount relative to that and
This course by the way is not some courses. There's oh yeah
This book you might want to look at it once in a while
But actually the course has nothing to do with it this course the book and the courts are one
they're very tied together there'll be parts of
the book that
we don't go into all the details that are in the book sometimes, but we expect you to be able to figure it out and
So really the course in the book are tied together and they very much the the progress of the course the topics covered
How it's covered everything about it is?
Consistent with the book and we wrote the book because of the course think of them as course notes
So and the reason why we are teaching this term by the way, we haven't taught together in several years
but because this is the first roll out of this book and
Not only is it being used here
But it's actually used by about 250 schools around the world and many of those people are also
Going through the same
activities of
teaching for it from this new edition for the first time and
So we wanted to make sure all the material for the course was sort of put in order and things
because other universities and other colleges use this material of
The supporting material we've developed so that's the course and today
Is the first lecture we're sort of doing a tag team here?
I'll talk the high level what the course is about what the main themes are and
Dave will talk more about the logistics
So we refer the the saying we have when?
the very first time I typed the number of this course
into a
Text Editor. I realized. I have typed those five digits many times in my career because it's the zip code of
CMU one five two one three (15-213) so that's where we come up with the same
so um
There's a few things about this course for the most part
You know in your normal undergraduate curriculum when you've learned programming
You've been very much separated from the realities of the machine you just think about code just
You put some text into some
little box somehow and outcomes of behavior that
It hopefully is what you intended the program to do the purpose of this course is to give you enough
understanding of what that box is doing when it executes your code and
Through that to help you
um
Become better at what you're trying to do so some of the outcomes is
There's really two types of outcomes from this course one
Is that if this is the only system's course you ever take in your whole life you will get useful
material from it you will learn tools
tricks methods that will help you if you ever are in involved in software development
large-scale software engineering projects
systems hardware design any aspect of computer technology
This will help you be better at what you do you'll understand what programs do
how they work what the machines that support them do why sometimes they work really well and why sometimes they don't work so well
It also is intended as a sort of stepping stone into a whole number of other courses at
CMU that will give you more in-depth understanding of computer technology
but our sort of specialized by topical area whether it's computer networking or operating systems or
embedded systems
where you'll take the sort of ideas from this course and be able to
Then learn in a somewhat narrower, but deeper sense what's really going on
And so it really is trying to serve those two goals of making you more effective giving you useful
ideas and tools right away, but also preparing you for later courses
So one way we talk about this instead of what why what kind of stuff will you learn from this course is
to go through a series of what we call great realities places where sort of computers meet up
real-life computers get meet up against your expectations
And maybe they're not quite the same
So one of them is and the first part of the course is going to take a fairly detailed look
How numbers are represented in computers?
And you'll learn some things that are on one hand surprising and another hand will start to make sense when you understand it better
So a simple case is
for numbers
I don't know when it was but it was probably in about eighth grade, Algebra that I learned that
If you square a number it will be at least zero if it's not an imaginary number
So a either an integer or a real number
You'd expect to square it and it to be a positive value or perhaps zero. Right?
And that's actually generally true with floats a representation of floating point numbers, but with
integers
Or int you know the computer representation of integers. It's not so clear
so for example if you square 40,000 on most computers, then you'll get
Whatever that should be
as you'd expect
But what if you square
50,000 so
You could do this in your head
But I actually built into this laptop is a computer, so I'm going to go ahead and use it
We just size it a little bit...
And use the tool
Which on Unix systems is called?
What's going on before...
Here we are on
Linux system is called GDB. But on a Macintosh OSX it's called LLDB
But they're pretty much the same program you will get to know this program really really well this terms
So like I said if you square 40,000
you'll get
What you'd expect?
But let's change this to 50,000
And you get a very peculiar number that doesn't look anything like you'd expect 50,000 squared to be and in fact. It's negative and
so that might just seem like well there must be a mistake or something no that that's just the way it is because
this computer is expecting numbers to be represented as 32-bit values and
the bit pattern that you get when you
do this multiplication
happens to be the representation of a negative number
so that's a an
example of where your normal
expectations about integer arithmetic may or may not hold
on the other hand
There are some places
like if I try to
Do the same thing multiplying 300 by 400 by 500 by 600 then all of a sudden
I also get a number that clearly is not what you'd expect because the same thing has happened
I've gotten an overflow
It happens that it's overflowed to a value that's positive not negative
But it still is obviously not the integer product of those four numbers
On the other hand one thing you'll find is
even though this arithmetic is now not a
normal sort of integer arithmetic
it actually has some well-behaved properties. So for example if you look at
what I've done is I just moved the 300 around from the beginning of the product to the end of the product and
So now if you think about how associativity and community works, I'm basically multiplying these four numbers in a different order
But what you see is you get the same
funny-looking result
No matter how you do it so what you can say from this is integer arithmetic is commutative and associative so it obeys
some of the conventional mathematical properties it just isn't what you'd expect it to be it's not a
a
normal sort of mathematical integer arithmetic
so
the cartoon here
shows an example that's a similar possibility we get to it
Oh, I guess it comes at the end I don't know
So the next question is a
addition
associative right can you order the numbers and then probably might have figured bolted and the integer arithmetic?
even though as this potential for overflow. It is associative, and it's commutative, too
But for floats. It's not really quite the same
Because the range of values you can get in floating pointers so extreme that some numbers kind of disappear on you
So the example I'll show without
Having to use a computer to do it is
if you take a big number and subtract it from itself you'll get zero so if you add that to 3.14 you'll get
3.14
but if you take
those two numbers and you reorder the
how you combine them so that that
3.14 compared to a -1e20 is so insignificant that that result gets turned into
-1e20 and you add that to 1e20 and you end up with zero
So it's not associative, and so what you see is
The both these number systems have some peculiarities and it all comes down to the fact that they use finite
representations of things that are potentially infinite in their expanse and
so there's some compromises in how those work and
what the compromise is you can overflow an integer and run out of room and
in floating point numbers you have roundoff problems where you should have drop the
digits that are significant you can also overflow floating points, but the more common problem is roundoff
So this is shown in this cartoon this idea of overflow of somebody counting sheep which in the u.s.
Is in English language at least a way to fall asleep and when
he or she goes from
32,767 and then increment set by one gets
-32,768 and we'll see exactly why that happens
but basically the numbers are going up to the
largest value can represent and then when it goes one more it becomes a negative number.
So these are really important things to understand. I mean
90% of the time maybe you can just get by
writing programs and not worrying about whether your numbers are going to exceed their possible range
But they sometimes when this could be really important if you're like
you know controlling a rocket you really don't want the positive
thrust to become negative or something like that, so you can see you there this could be an important consideration
similarly there's
well-known instances of security vulnerabilities
where somebody wrote code that sort of expected a
positive number in some place and a clever person figured out if I supply a negative number I can fool the system and get it
to do bad things
so these are the kind of
corner cases that you need to understand better if you're either working in programs where it's really really important that it worked correctly.
Or you're really worried about security vulnerabilities
anytime you have possible for corner cases you have to understand these nuances better.
A similarly for floating-point if you're going to use floating-point for serious computation whether it's scientific research or for
designing bridges or
nuclear power plants or something you better understand what the characteristics are
So that's our first one, and we'll spend a couple weeks talking about numbers and number of representations and their properties here
The second is we're going to spend a lot of time in this course learning about machine level programming meaning what the
instructions are that actually get executed by the computer and that can be
described in Assembly Language
Which is a text version of it or an object code which is the actual bit-level binary encoding of
instructions, and we'll learn a fair bit about that and spend amount of time seeing how
code that you write in C
gets turned into machine code and how that gets executed on the machine
One thing I'll say is that historically courses like this would teach
Assembly code by having you write
programs in Assembly that do
various things not usually very interesting because it's a lot of work to write assembly program
this course is much more about taking the assembly code that's been generated
by a compiler the  C compiler and
looking at it and understanding it. That's a different set of skills
than you need to write it on your own
And in particular, we're going to look at the language of of
Intel processors the most recent versions of them are called x86-64
The 64-bit version of their instruction set.
And one thing that's new in this course
compared to previous ones we used to teach 32-bit stuff
this course is
64-bits all the time
Another one that we'll talk about a fair amount that is
really fairly visible to programmers surprisingly visible is
aspects of the memory system.
So modern computers have a very complex layered memory system
to try and give you high performance in high capacity at the same time.
And there's some results of that system that can mean that
if you program write a program
well it might work really well
And if you don't it could run very poorly because it's not making use of this hierarchical memory system
So and also there's a lot of bugs that show up especially in C programs
that have to do with memory referencing errors.
And so, understanding
what those errors are what their manifestation is how to prevent them is a big part of the course
So for example if I define a struct that contains two integer
values a in an array and a double precision floating point number d
and if I
this function fun you'll see what it does is it's given an argument i and it
sets the i's element of a to some
strange-looking value
so
As you know I should really only be either 0 or 1
with this code because that's the range of possible values of this array a
but
we can try other things too, so
In particular if you run it on either one or two
You'll get what you'd expect that
you assigned a 3.14 to element d of this structure and
When you read it back you get the same thing
and in fact, but now if I set a of two
To this number all of a sudden, you'll see that my floating-point number which
seems to have nothing to do with a has changed and if I do that same thing with I
equal to three you'll see I get a number that's closer to two then to 3.14 and
if I keep going
well nothing much happens until I
hit
6 and then the program crashes
so
Something interesting is going on here at least something quirky is going on and the reason is again
it has to do with how data is laid out in memory and
how its accessed and one of the features of C and C++
is it doesn't do any bounds checking on a race it will happily let you
reference element number 5 million of a two element array and not complain
But the operating system might complain as it did here and it
in this particular structure
And we'll see more about how structures are implemented and laid out,
but basically the two if each of these
blocks in this vertical chain represents 4 bytes and so the two elements of a each are 4 bytes
d is 8 bytes and then there's some other
stuff in the other
beyond that's not actually in the struct itself
so you'll see that if I
reference either a of 0 or a of 1
Then I will just modify that array is designed
But when I'm calling fun of 2 or fun of 3
what I'm actually doing is altering
The the bytes that encode this number d
and that's why you saw the sort of funny numbers come out of it and
As I go up at some point when I hit 6 I'm
modifying some state of the program that
it's using to kind of keep things organized most likely how it
Keeps track of of allocated memory, and that's causing the program to crash
so this is a pretty good demonstration of a
Why C programming can drive you crazy
Because as you saw it doesn't do bounds checking
so it's easy to write code that
does invalid stuff
It's also
often the case that
you'll cause some problem, and it has a sort of action a distance feature that you can modify some think you're
Modifying some data structure and what you're doing because of the way things are organized in memory
You're changing something totally unrelated somewhere else in the program
You'd imagine. They're not just one apart, but they're 10,000 apart and
things might just run fine for
hours days or weeks
and then always say at some point that data that got corrupted a long time ago gets accessed and
something goes wrong, so
This can be some of the worst nightmare debugging nightmares that exist on Earth is to try and figure out memory referencing herbs
So this is actually one argument not to program in C or C++
and it's a valid argument, I'll admit.
But also as a
person who's writing a lot of C
programming you just get more experienced,
and you know at times that you should actually put bounds checking in your own code
and there's also tools available that will help you
bulletproof your code so that it will detect these kind of problems, so it's not like you have to change languages
But it is a particular feature of these languages
and so understanding sort of the machine-level representation of Data Structures
And how they work is very really makes a huge difference in your ability to
deal with these kind of vulnerabilities and things of vulnerabilities by the way
also from a security perspective
The the fourth Sort of theme, we'll cover in the course is getting performance out of programs
Other parts of the curriculum in CS do much more emphasis on getting the right
Algorithm at the right Data Structure, and that's really well and good.
It's important stuff, I don't deny it. But they some amount of the
sort of
Low-level optimization that you need to do that.
You need to understand what the system does what makes it run well,
what makes it run poorly in order to be able to do that kind of optimization
So the example. We like to use is
These two functions do exactly the same thing in terms of their their behavior what they do is
Copy a
Matrix or Array
from called source or src to a destination DST.
They're both size to be
2048 rows
2048 columns two-dimensional arrays
And you'll see that the programs do the obvious thing
you have a nested pair of loops to do the row and column
indices and you just copy from
One source element to a destination element the only thing that's different
you'll see is that the two
loops
their nesting is different the nesting order is different in one case. I'm going kind of row first
Going through all the rows and then the columns and the other is for any given row. I'm copying all the columns
That's really the only difference between these two programs
but what you'll find if you run it on a typical system is
that that one is much faster than the other in this particular machine
we ran it on it was about close to 20 times difference in performance
So something fishy is going on if the same program that differs only in this seemingly
insignificant way a way that has no effect whatsoever on its functionality can have this much performance difference and
so to understand this
You need to stare at the cover of the book
because basically
You're two different points of this
strange-looking picture that's on your book and since there's no axes or labels on it. It makes no sense whatsoever
But it's there
so what you see is this picture shows four different memory access patterns, and I won't go into the details of
what the throughput measured in megabytes per second on on a
basically a copying program was and
without going into the details what you'll see is these two functions sort of sit at different points in this memory access pattern
the one that goes through row by row is much better than the one that goes through column by column and
as a result you're getting a lot better performance that it has to do with this memory Hierarchy and what they call the cache memories
That you're getting way better
performance out of it in case than the other so
that's explains what the cover of the book is about and
we'll talk about it more later in the course and
Then a final part of the course talks more about not just getting computers to run little programs in isolation
but getting computers that talk to each other over networks and implement services like
web servers and other functions like that which of course is where
Most in the world of computing sits today. It's not just
isolated machines, but computers that
interact with each other over the network.
They're embedded controllers that are
interacting with the physical world, so
Really the the world of computers is a much richer
environment and will cover at least some aspects of that in the final part of this course
so as
I mentioned the other feature of this course is it will get you ready for other systems
courses you might take it CMU and here we listed actually a subset of the courses
at the University that require this course is a prerequisite and
They're mostly in Computer Science and ECE
But you'll see. It's quite a range of of different courses and
each of them builds on
say one or multiple aspects of the material you learn in the course, so
The reason why we make everyone take this course including incoming master students is
That all these other courses at the university have come to rely on
students being familiar and having done the work of two thirteen
or five thirteen as a prerequisite and they can build on that material and
sort of cover more ground as a result rather than having to do what would otherwise be
Somewhat remedial work on it and in fact one of the part of the genesis of this course was the people who taught
the operating system course
sort of complained that they were spending too much time at the beginning of the course talking about some very basics of machine programming and
Dave and I said oh well we can cover that so that was part of what got this course started
And as I mentioned that the course has a sort of perspective that's very different from traditional
Systems courses most systems courses including that whole array saw there were about how do I build some
Particular feature, how do I implement an operating system How do I design a pipeline microprocessor
And don't it's all important stuff to know we really want the people who are out there
Building operating systems and designing microprocessors to have learned how to do it
On the other hand is a way to sort of get new into this and get the introduction and get the experience
We find it more useful to take what we call a programmers perspective meaning
understanding of
What you as a person who sits in front of a computer screen and types code I need to know about that machine
You're typing code for in order to be effective at doing it as opposed to
Somebody who some day going to be designing the actual machine itself?
so that
by taking that perspective it gives you sort of an
Understanding so now when you go off to implement it
you'll actually know what these features are and why it's important to implement them well
But also that by doing this programmers perspective it lets you
Right away get tools that you can use in other places where you're writing programs are doing anything related to it
And be more effective at that, so this programmers perspective really gives this dual
benefit to it that
We feel is very useful and students have taken the course in the past have expressed that as well
So as I mentioned the we have two instructors
for the course and
They also happen to be authors and the longest
We've probably taught this course
More than anyone else, but it's also taught by other people on campus as well
So what I'm going to do now is hand my pair of microphones over two days
All right, welcome good afternoon. It's great to see you. My name is Dave wilhelm hren and
I'm just delighted to have the opportunity to
Be one of your instructors this term
this course is
One of the reason I'm so excited to be teaching this course. I mean, I just love this course and
The real reason is the the opportunity of represents to have an impact on
people's lives
We really believe that the material you learned this semester
can help a really positive and long-lasting impact on on your careers and
It'll help you not only with your future classes, but also
Future positions you have and I hear this from people all all the time
Former CMU students and
Students around the world to have taken the equivalent of 213 at their schools
even a
couple years ago
We were interviewing a faculty member finished tenure-track faculty member who went to did his undergrad at CMU
and then went off to Stanford got his PhD at Stanford and was coming back to
you know join the faculty and
He told me that 213 changed his life in our interview, and I don't know if he was trying to butter me up
but I I think I believe him he he said it changed his whole life in the sense that it gave him a
Research Direction, you know he didn't really know what
What he knew it kind of like computer science,
but it didn't really know what direction to go and and after he took to 213
He knew they wanted to to do his word was life's work in systems
now
it was just remarkable right to come back and have we ended up actually hiring him and
He told me that everybody in his lab at stanford all of the grad students had a copy of a book on their desk
front and they were from all over
You know all different schools
and so I mean I even I was in a bookstore in Beijing a
couple Years ago right outside the PKU campus and
I was up on the fifth floor trying to see if I could find a copy of the textbook and I found the
English version in one aisle and
then a couple aisles over I found the Chinese version I was
Going through the Chinese version and the sky tapped me on my shoulder
and I turned around he says oh man that that book is really good. You should the English version is two aisles over
and I mean
It just blew me away to be
to be in the head of someone like
Halfway around the world. It was just that it was just one of those moments, and so I'm
I'm not trying to boast. I'm just trying what I want
I want to give you the sense of what it what an opportunity this course represents for I to
to have what we hope will be a
really positive impact on on your lives
so
let me we have kind of a
kind of a funny organization for the course to it in response to that just that the tremendous demand
We have we found that we have for it
So there's there's actually three course numbers
But it's all the same course okay. It's identical course
15-513 is for our master students
and the 513
513 doesn't have a formal lecture. So there's no seats assigned to it
instead we'll videotape the lectures and
we'll make those available on the course web web page for our for our graduate students and
the reason we do this is just because
in the past well, we
We didn't have enough seats for everyone and there would be cases where there might be a hundred 150
master students on the waitlist
They wouldn't be able to get into the course and we we didn't really want that because they need this course for to take other
courses
So that's the reason why we have this
This sort of does not meet version of 213 is
513 because we can admit as many all the master's students that that need to take the course
now
15 to 13 and 18 to 13 or are for undergraduates in
Computer Science and ECE
respectively
okay, and
The undergraduates will go to lectures and recitations
okay, in person graduate students will watch videotapes of those but otherwise yes
For those videotapes will they be available...?
Yeah, we're making them available to everyone actually
Sorry and lecture slides as well. Everything is available on the course web page, so
So you'll be doing
The all of students will have equal access to office hours
the staff mailing list and
everybody does the same labs and
The same exams okay, so it's just a question
it's just a matter of whether you're good a lecture in person or if you're watching on video in fact if
You know since it's available to everybody if you miss lecture, it'll be there on the web page
And you can catch up which I know you'll probably do actually I know most of you will never miss class, right?
But the few of you who do you'll be able to watch the video?
Okay
All right, this is the one part I list the part I hate
I love teaching that this is this is the one part teaching that
None of us really like but we have to talk about it, and that's academic integrity
if you're new on campus
coming from a international school if you're an international student new on campus
there might be different notions of academic integrity and
different notions of cheating at your
undergraduate school or your old school
So if you're new on campus pay very close attention to this because at Carnegie Mellon, we take academic integrity
very seriously okay. It's not a wink wink, nod nod
we're very serious about it
And we want you we want everybody doing their own work to preserve the integrity of the courses
So what exactly is cheating?
so if you share code with anybody either
copying
retyping looking at somebody's code like if you look at somebody's code on the screen
or if you give somebody a file all of those all of those
examples of sharing are cheating
If if you describe your code like line by line to somebody that's cheating
If you coach somebody line by line, that's cheating
Searching the web for solutions. Just the act of searching is cheating
and this is a
this is a real problem for us in particular because the course is offered all around the world and
People either maliciously or or sometimes just they're proud of their work, and they post it. You know for employers on like public GitHub sites
So it's it might be tempting to to search for these solutions
but even the act of searching is cheating and
definitely if you find some a solution in and use it that's cheating even if you modify it afterwards and
And I just want you to remember I can  know how to use Google just as well as anybody else right so I
can search for solutions too
so
Copying code. You know you might be tempted
You might be tempted to copy code from someone who took the class you know in a previous semester
Don't do it. That's that's cheating too
Now what's not cheating so you can you can help each other use tools
you know somebody's having trouble using GDB or you know they have questions about how to run
Use a text editor that's stuffs all great. You can help each other out
Using the tools how to log into the Shell machines all of that kind of stuff
and you
can help you can discuss sort of high-level design issues, and that's probably a good idea. Yes
Yeah, yeah, did you take it a previous semester oh
Okay, yeah the question was if you took it in a previous semester can use your your work and the answer is yes
So it you can also talk to each other about high level you know design issues
you know, how are you are using an explicit list or using a
Segregated list for your Malik lab. Okay that kind of stuff is is is okay, okay high level okay?
Low-level not okay
And basically what we want you to write your own code
This is not you know. It's kind of a cut and paste world these days right.
You look stuff up on Google, Stackoverflow
You cut and paste it
But that's not that's not the way. We do it here
we want you to do the work yourself. We want you to enjoy the experience of figuring things out and learning how to solve problems
now the consequences for cheating
There's a single sanction
if
You're caught cheating you'll you'll be expelled from the course with an
There's no exceptions all right if you drop the course we'll just reinstate you and then flunk you
it's really a
It's a very serious very serious
Penalty because we just take it. We take it so seriously at at sub
And it's just it's just something we don't want you to do
We have amazing tools to detect code plagiarism
We have amazing tools to detect plagiarism that are
that are resilient to
renaming
Reformatting they operate at a very deep syntactic level
and
So just please please don't do it
We have I think 18 tas will have office hours almost every day of the week
There's plenty of opportunities and ways to get help
start early
If you get stuck start early enough so that you get stuck you can go ask for help
we have the
automatic extensions built-in if you need more time I'll talk about that later
form of Grace days
But please please whatever you do
Don't cheat
It's just tragic when it happens last last fall 25 students were expelled from the course
Some were expelled from the university
because it was a second offense
Many were sent home. I talked to students who were like the only person in their family to go to college
The only person in their village to go to college, and they were going home
Without without a degree, and it's just tragic. It's just
So please please please
Don't do it do your own work
and
It'll be a wonderful experience
Randy mentioned the the textbook is computer systems the programmers perspective third edition
you can there's a whole bunch of
Supporting material on the on the books website at csapp.cs.cmu.edu
and as randy mentioned this this book really matters for the course because actually the book came out of the course right, so
The book is the course, the course is the book on and
So it'll it'll really help you. Love it the labs that we do come directly from material that we discuss in the book
So what I would encourage all of you to do, and I'm not sure if anybody has ever taken this advice
But I say it every year anyway, because I believe it
But I think a really good strategy for studying and preparing for this course would be to read each chapter three times
Okay, read it three times
work the practice problem, so we have littered throughout the book or practice problems with solutions at the end of the
the end of the chapter and these practice problems are like little sort of bite-size morsels just to kind of
just to kind of check your
Kind of Sanity check of your understanding of the material
So I think if you've read this if you read the book
each chapter three times and work the practice problems you it that would be an excellent way to
Go through the semester and prepare
The other book we use is the Kernighan and Richies classic C programming book
I think
this is still this was written a long time ago
It's still the best book around. I think for C. It's a it's a beautiful
Example of technical writing it was one of the inspirations
I used when I was writing the book you know I tried to find that same clarity and
precision that they that they
Kernighan and Richies
Have in their book, so this is a this is a really good book. I mean, this is kind of book
It's a reference, but it's a kind of book
you can just read from beginning to end and get a really good understanding of C
There's a there's four main components to the course there's lectures where we go over the high-level concepts
recitations where which meet
Once a week for an hour
led by a TA and the purpose of the recitations is really to help you with the labs right so it's very practical and hands-on
There's
There's seven of those labs
And these are really the heart and soul of the course this is where
This is where all the real learning comes in I think when you actually have to do this stuff
And that's why we take the cheating part so seriously because if you do these labs
You're going to learn an incredible amount of really cool stuff
if you don't do them you won't learn anything
So each one of these these labs is one or two weeks each
and
involves
Typically some kind of programming or measurement
there's also two exams a midterm and a final the
The exams are proctored
They're online
proctored in
Wien and and gates and what we do for the exams is we have like we take like four days
From 10:00 to 10:00 and then you can sign up
and then we have like multiple clusters that are network isolated and then you can sign up for a slot like a 6-hour slot and
the
Midterm is like nominally like an hour eighty minute exam. That's the same exam
Where you we gave when we used to have people sitting in person so it's nominally like 80 minutes
but we give you like a five or six hour window to do it okay, so there's
So you can sign up any time any day that there's a slot, okay
So there's flexibilities that can kind of tailor it to your your schedule, and we I think we've also removed all the time pressure
right so which is
you can you can go back you can check your work you can you can just kind of relax and
not
not not be worried about
how quickly you do it
now there's many different ways to get help the main source of information is the course webpage that's a
www.cmu.edu/~213
and all the information is [there] we've got a complete schedule of lectures and assignments
We don't change it that it's fixed it. So you can look at that and and plan your semester
Knowing that those dates of won't change we've actually even got all of the lectures posted ahead of time for
For the other instructors around the world who are using the book so we needed to get them all already
There's also news at at the very beginning. There's sort of news if we need to make announcements. We'll post it there
We don't use either blackboard or piazza in the course
instead we have a
staff mailing list
That you can that you can send mail to if you have questions and all of the tas and all of the faculty are
Subscribed to that staff mailing list and so we'll all see it
and
We usually we try to have you know really fast feedback, right so there's so many people
so many people looking at
your emails that chance is very high you'll get an answer back quickly the
Disadvantage of having this advantage of this mailing list is that it allows us to control the message
And control what we're it's what feedback
We're giving back to you the disadvantage is that we often get the same question over and over again and so for that
We've established a FAQ if we find we're getting same questions over and over
We've established a FAQ on the on the course web page
for sort of organized by labs ok so you can
You can see the answers to frequently asked questions on the there
We have office hours. I think we're still trying to eat. We we're still trying to meet
with the staff and figure out the exact office hours, but what I'm
What we're thinking now is that we'll have office hours so six days a week, okay every day. That's Saturday
The they will be at the same time in same place every day so from 5:45
to
8:30
in a queen 5207 cluster
Will have 213 tas there to to help to answer your questions okay
So you don't have to make
Appointments, I mean you can make an appointment to see any staff member of course
But you don't you you know that at the same time same place every day. There's somebody you can go to for help
Okay for our labs and exams every assignment
Every lab is a single person so we don't have any group projects
We want you to do the work yourself now
You know it's important to work in groups, and you will learn how to work in groups and other classes
See us classes, but not in 213 we want this is a kind of a core course we want you to figure stuff out yourself
All of our hand ends will be due at 11:59 p.m.
on either a Tuesday or Thursday, and this is you can see which on the
schedule page on the course webpage
And all of our handings are using auto Lab
where
You know you've probably used it for some of your other classes, but it's a it's
a auto grading service that allows you to get instant feedback on your
on your on your hand in so when you hand it in you get feedback right away
The exams like I mentioned are going to be a network isolated clusters
held over multiple days and and you can just sign up for a
Slot that's available now
What usually happens is if we offer like the exam
Tuesday, Wednesday, and Thursday the Thursday slot still up immediately
and so
You know I guess I
Should try to try to sign up soon if you want
but people always seem to want to defer to the end rather than and this is me I'd want to get it over with but
So I just thought that is sort of a constraint right that if you can only sign up for slots that
That are available
Okay, now you know we make mistakes. There's we always make mistakes, especially with just so many students
so we there's a there's a
Specific process for appealing grades if you think that there was a that, you're the work wasn't graded properly
So what you do after after either an exam or after your labs are graded
You have 7 days to file an appeal and appeals have to be in in writing and hardcopy
okay, so there's no we won't we won't we won't consider any email any appeals via email
It has to be in writing and hardcopy and you give those to me, and if I'm not there
you can just slide it under the desk ok and
What the reason we do it that way is it allows us to treat
everybody fairly, so we get all the appeals together at once and
Then we can we can we can treat everybody the same way rather than just sort of doing them one at a time like that
ok
Now for our labs we have
ten machines that were donated by Intel called the shark machines
so initially our first version of 213
and
I guess we started using intel machines in 1999 we used to alpha
processors for the first year I like to fish
So all of our machines were they were called the fish machines right they were freshwater fish
and then we upgraded a few years after that and those were the saltwater fish machines, and then we upgraded
like in 2011 to these nehalem class servers
And run out of fresh water fish and saltwater fish, so the next grade up was sharks, right?
So every fish is it's named after some kind of shark
But these are the same machines that that you'll that auto lab uses for grading right? So there's some consistency for
performance-Oriented labs like Malloc Lab
And you can access them
That you the names are listed on the course webpage and so you can ssh to a specific machine
They're all identical if you have an Andrew account
You've already got accounts on the machines, right
So there's nothing special to do or you can just ssh to shark.ics and it'll just randomly put you on on
one of the shark machines
Okay, if if you have any trouble logging in just send send mail to the staff mailing list
Okay, we know that during the semester things come up
grandparents died especially near the near the final
That's harsh I know
But that things come up right, and you've got your very busy, you're taking a lot of courses
so instead of sort of dealing with requests for extensions and
You know all these special cases what we do is. We give you five grace days
that you can then spend as you wish
So if you hand your work in late one day late,
you'll automatically consume a grace day, okay
we don't allow you to sort of allocate the grace days
you spend one of your grace days by handing in late
So if you have a great day less than you hand in late
You'll spend that grace day, but you won't be penalized for the late hand in
and so we have five grace days
over the entire semester
and
a maximum of two grace days
For the assignments now we're going to set up since the first three assignments are kind of
not as programming intensive
And don't take as much time
we're not going to allow any great days for those because a
One Grace day one sorry one great day and then for the the latter four labs which are much more intense
we're going to allow you to a max of two great states and the reason we're doing this is because we
Don't want you to burn you're good these great days are valuable
They're critical especially later in the semester when have you really really dizzy
So we don't want you to burn off your grace days early in the semester and this happens every semester
And it's and then when alec lab comes up. There's no gray space left, and it's really it's really sad to see that
And so we're going to limit you to one for those first three
Just to help you save you from yourself
now
it
The the the nominal late penalty if you don't have a great days fifteen percent per day
and
We don't allow any hand in three days after the due date at all so that live shuts off
And then that's it
now if there's some kind of catastrophic event you know then you know please contact us for
an extension right so we're not you know we try to be reasonable, but most of the most of the
Most of the reasons that for requesting extensions. You can handle yourself
Using your Graces days
and just I mean this is that this is advice that give every semester too but I
but it's people often don't don't pay attention but or
just
They're unable to but but really for every one of these assignments you want to start early
and the reason is you need to give yourself time to to go seek help if you get stuck
because the nature of these very programming intensive assignments like we have in 213 is that you're going to get stuck and
And often it's very hard to to bound the time you spend on on some of these assignments
You know it's not like problem sets where you can kind of predict you know this will take
There's no taking like three hours to do these problem sets
For a lot of the 213 assignments. It's very difficult to
To sort of manage your time and bound your time
So for that reason you really want to start early to give yourself a chance to get help when you get stuck
Now in the lecture hall of you're permitted to have your laptop
but we ask you not to
Send email or instant messaging or cell phone texting or anything like that if you here we want you to to be attentive and engaged
the
Your presence in lectures and recitations is voluntary so we don't take
We don't take role at either of those
We encourage you to come, but it's not required
And no recordings of any kind except this one
Okay, the exams and labs are weighted equally 50% midterms 20 finals 30
And final grades are based on a straight 90 80 70
scale
Now rough outline of the semester
the first three labs cover programs reference the machine representations of programs and data
Data lab is how we teach you about fit level representations of data
So you'll sell collection of puzzles and see like a puzzle might be is
a little function
That you have to implement and like absolute value so a function that returns the absolute value of its art input argument
The kicker is that we restrict the set of operators that you can use and it has to be straight line code
no conditionals or loops and
So to solve these puzzles so imagine how you might try to solve absolute value without using an if statement
right the normal way to do it would be if x less than zero return x
or Negative x
See I told you we make mistakes
but imagine how you might do that without using conditionals and only using bit level C operations
Right, so this is how this is how this is our way of teaching you
How data is really represented in the machine now the bomb Lab which you've probably heard at this is
this is a kind of famous all over the world now and
at CMU the bomb lab is the way we teach you how to read and understand assembly language and
a bomb just briefly a
bomb is a is a C program that consists of a collection of six phases and
Each Phase wants you to type something in at the keyboard
If you type in the what it wants you to type what it expects you to type?
then you've diffused that phase and
it goes to the next phase then you have to type with that phase once and
If you defuse all the phases then you've defuse the bomb
however if you type in the wrong thing then the bomb explodes by printing boom
and you have to try it again
and the kicker is in either case when if you explode the bomb
or defuse a
phase that information gets sent to auto Lab if you and
We use the defusing string that that your bomb sends us
And we check it out on a copy of your bomb that we keep on the server
That's another thing every everybody gets a different bomb
slightly different bomb
so we check so
When you defuse when you just use the phase auto lab takes the string that it
that your bomb sends us and then compares against the local copy of your bomb if
You explode phase you lose half a point
So there's a real consequence to exploding a bomb it's very very tense
until you learn how to use GDB to set a breakpoint
Before the function that sends the information to the server
And we want you to do that right so a bombs are really
The bombs really beautiful. It's kind of fun. It's kind of like a video game
it it teaches you how to read compiler generated code because
The only oh the kicker is sorry the kicker is we don't give you the source code all we give you is the binary
Hence the binary bomb so in order to defuse a bomb you've got to fire up GDB
single trace through the find where the code is for each phase single trace through that code and
sort of reverse engineer and figure out what it wants you to type in and
then you'll quickly find out where that function that explodes the bomb is and you'll put a breakpoint there and
so we want you to do that because
The bomb besides teaching you how to program assembly language it also
Teaches you sort of organically how to use GDB because you really can't do it if you don't use if you don't run GDB
and
Then the the third lab is this is a new lab the semester
the Randy's developed called the attack Lab and
We developed this lab specifically for 64-bit architecture, so this is a reflection of the change from 32 bits to 64 bits
And this is really excited about this one. You'll learn how to
You'll learn how to write exploits using
Return to a sort of a modern technique called return to return oriented programming which is kind of the modern
Modern way that hackers deal with the fact that stacks in
newer machines
move around and
and are
prohibitive
And make an impossible to execute code on the on the stack, so this the brand new labs really
I think it's really going to be
Really going to be neat
In the memory Hierarchy when we study the memory Hierarchy
we have a cache lab called the cache lab
Where you'll build your own cache simulator,
so this is how you sort of learn how
this hardware
That randy was mentioning called it cache Memory works
You'll build a simulator and see for that and then you'll take a small transpose function
And you'll try to make that that code run with as few misses as possible on your simulator and this will involve
Sort of understanding of how the memory Hierarchy works and how to exploit it
the part of the course where you we sort of transitioned from Hardware to
interacting with the the system software that the operating system
There's sort of a concept
That we call exceptional Control Flow that
exists in all parts of the system
and it sort of represents that intellectual transition from hardware to software so
this is how
This was sort of a key idea that allowed us to kind of smoothly
move from from Hardware to Software
in some intellectually consistent way and
So the the ideas that you cover an exceptional control flow like low hard
Low-level Hardware interrupts and exceptions and
Then at the higher level sort of involving hardware and operating system software is the idea of an opera of the process context switch
ok, so this is this is where you start to learn what processes are and how to
how to ask the Kernel to create in
manage processes for you at the next higher level or a
software form of exceptional control flow called a signal
so this exists solely on the Linux Kernel and
Then and then even at a higher level at there's an application C language version of exceptional control flow
Call set Jump and long jump
So this this notion of exceptional control flow kind of exists in all parts of the system. We covered all at once
And the lab that we use
to sort of exercise all these ideas is
Called the shell lab and in the shell lab you'll write your own Linux shell
Which is really cool, so that's the program the command line program that you interact with whenever you log into a linux box
You're going to write your own
And I don't look for me
That was really exciting when I could like write something that looked like a real shell. It was pretty neat
The next area is well study is called Virtual memory
Virtual memory is a sort of combination of hardware and software
that presents an abstraction to you of this variant of memory is a very large array of bytes
When in reality memory is a Hierarchy of hardware and of cache memories and DRAM virtual memory
Provides a very high-level abstraction and as just a linear sequence of bytes
It also does provide a lot of a lot of other useful abstractions that make many different parts of the system
Much easier to manage ok so we'll learn we learn about virtual memory
we'll learn how it works. We'll learn about the performance impact potential performance impact that it has on your programs
And and we'll also learn how to manage
That large pool of memory that it makes available to you and the lab that we do that
the lab where you'll do that is called Malloc lab and in the malloc lab you'll write your own malloc and free
functions so you'll you'll reinvent the functionality of the lib C malloc and free and this is a
Maybe it's two pages of code, but it'll be a guarantee.
It'll be the most sophisticated
difficult two pages of code you've written
Not only because since it's managing the memory system. You can't use all of I mean C
Doesn't have many, C Doesn't help you out a lot
with
abstractions for Data Structures, but when you're writing
But at least it does give you ideas like Struct, Union that you can use to
Structure your memory when you're writing a malloc package you can't use any of those
You have to ride
exclusively on pointers and casting
because you
malloc task is working at such a low level
And so it's a very very difficult piece of code
For that reason, but also the design space for malloc is is enormous you have many options
They all have implications that trade-off performance and a memory efficiency
and
finally in the last part of the course
we deal with I/O
Input/Output so so far in the course we've just talked about sort of running programs
On machines in the last part of the course we'll talk about input and output sending data
into and out of the machine
so we'll look at basic concepts of Linux I/O
will
And since I think the most interesting form of I/O is is networking which allows you to talk to machines anywhere in the world
Using the Internet, we'll also talk we'll learn how to do network programming you'll learn how to write programs that
Use the sockets interface
which is the basic interface for the internet to talk to machines any potentially any machine in the in the world and
That's really exciting. I mean once I can still remember when
developing this course. I had two windows open on my machine
I was ssh into two different machines, and I wrote a program to send a message like hello world
from one machine to the other and when that hello world appeared on the second windows like so exciting
I mean if you're a nerd it's really exciting
but
but just the thought that
That could have been at any machine right that could have been any machine that does just like opens up a whole new world
Okay, all of our
all of our hands are using a system called auto lab which was developed here, and you can access it if you
if you are on the roster as of this morning if you go to the auto Lab link
Then you'll see this course was based on your page
if you're not enrolled
you won't have an auto lab account
and you have to be enrolled to get an auto lab account, so
if you want to try to wait it out, and wait for people to drop. I'll make the first couple of
elite the first assignment due available from the course web page, so you can work on it without
actually handing into auto lab but at least you can keep going
Okay, if you enroll actually I didn't update this but I updated the auto lab accounts today
Now one final thing if you have waitlist questions
Please don't
don't send email to the staff because we don't control the waiver, so
You should contact one of these either Cathy Catherine or Zara depending on which class you had
Okay, so that's that welcome again looking forward to a great semester, and we'll see you on Thursday