Good afternoon everybody welcome
Good to see you
so today, we're going to study a
Arcane area of computer systems known as floating point
Which is the way that computer systems represent?
the real numbers
So you're all familiar with?
decimal decimals you know something like 3.14 and
There's a similar a similar idea with with binary numbers
okay, so uh
So what what?
does a
fractional binary number Like 1 0 1 1
point 1 0 1
Represent and how does that work?
well, it works just like the
decimal fractional decimal numbers that you use to
So you have a in this case that they it's a binary point and to the left of the binary point
You have bit position to representing powers of 2 so 2 to the 0?
2 to the 1 2 to the 2
So 1/2
I'm sorry 1 2 4 and so on and
to the right of the binary point
You have 2 to the minus 1?
1/2 2 to the minus 2 1 4 2 to the minus 3 1 a and so on and so we can we can represent
any
fractional binary number
using
Using this notation where we sum?
Each the bit at Position K
Times 2 to the k ok
Ok so it's really it really works exactly the same way as as with base 10, just just with Base 2
So let's look at some of these
some of these values so 5 and 3/4 we would represent as 1 0 1 point 1 1
So this this is before
plus 1 is 5 plus
1/2 Plus
1/4 okay, so
2/4 Plus 1/4 is 3/4 so 5 and 3/4 ok so, that's pretty simple
2 and 7/8
is 1 zero point 1 1 1
so that
1 0 is 2 of course and
then point 1 1 1 is 1/2, so
4 eighths plus
1/4 is two eighths plus
1/8 okay, so seven eight
and 1
7/16
would be one point zero 1 1 1 so the one to the left of the binary point is 1 and
then we have
1/4
Plus 1/8 Plus 1/16
so one 1/4 is
4 16
1/8 is to 16 and
1/16 so you add those after you get 7/16
Okay now notice that for some of these numbers. We this bit this bit pattern
101.1 1 if We shift it to the right to get 1 0.111?
We've divided by 2 right, so we've taken 5 and 3/4 and divided it by 2 and it
It works the other way too if you shift
to the left you multiply if you shift to the Left by 1 you multiply by 1 and
these numbers that
are all ones to the right of the
Of the binary point are these are numbers that are just slightly less than than one okay?
And so we'll well we want to represent those will often
Will sometimes refer to those numbers of that form as 1 minus epsilon and ePsilon just?
Depends on how many bits you have to the right of the binary point so ePsilon gets smaller the more?
The more of those bits you have there it gets closer to 1 and epsilon gets smaller the more of those fits you have
now there's a
There's limitations
In this kind of representation so first of all we can only represent
rational numbers of the Form X Divided by 2 2 to the K
we can only represent numbers of that's form exactly other numbers have to get
Have repeating bit representations that can't be represented
The finite number of debts that we have in a computer system
So for example things like a 1/3 is that is this repeating representation?
1/5 and 1/10 there are other examples of that
Now the other problem. We have is that we can only
There's only so many bits to the left and the right of the the binary point. So we're kind of
if we put if we move the binary point to the left
Then we don't have as many we can't represent as many
Large numbers we can only represent small numbers, but we have more precision to the right of the binary point
So we can represent more fractional values just the range of those values will be much smaller
similarly if we move the binary point to the right
We'll have a larger range of values, but we won't build a represent as many fractions, okay?
so there's this there's this kind of trade-off and
floating point is a
representation to
That to try that that enables us to move that
Basically to move that binary point to represent sort of as wide a range as possible
with as much precision
given the number of bits the finite number of bits that we have to work with so the
The float and floating point is this sort of shifting binary point right this floating this floating binary point?
now up until
Floating point was just a disaster
and
every computer manufacturer had their own
representation
You couldn't and it was just terrible because you couldn't predict
What would happen what would happen if you moved your program from one machine to another?
The Behavior would be different the rounding would be different
It was a very difficult situation and people really
computer scientists in particular really
disliked floating point
in
in 18
1985 I triple E which is the professional association for electrical engineers?
Introduced a and it's also a very
Important standards body they introduced a standard floating-point representation called I triple e floating point
Which was then adopted by all computer manufacturers?
So now the situation is much better everybody everybody supports the same kind of floating point
Representation which is what we're going to learn about today
so the floating point
has the form
it represents numbers in a like a scientific notation it represents numbers of the form
minus 1 to the s
Where s is assigned it?
Times A
significant M
ok times
2 to some exponent e ok so all of the numbers that we can represent in floating point
Have to be represented in this form
So the sign bit s determines whether the number is negative or positive
obviously
the significant M and sometimes sometimes called the Mantissa
where the M comes from the significant m normally is a fractional value in the range between
between 1 & 2 and we'll see we'll see why that is in a second and
then the exponent E weights the value by some power of -
Okay, so this is encoded in
in either 32 bits or 64 bits in the following way the the sign bit s is the most significant bit and
then this is followed by some number of
By it by some number of bits called the Exp field
Which encodes?
the exponent e of
But it's not identical to e it encodes e, and we'll see how that works and then
the frack and then and then that's followed the remaining bits are the
the Frack Field
Which encodes them but isn't identical to em?
Now we I?
Triple E floating point has provides two different kinds
Of floating-point their single precision 32 bits and so-called double precision which is 64 bits
There's this funky
Intel
Extended precision which is non-standard and we won't talk about it anymore
And so in the single precision 32 bits you have one sign, bit. There's always a sign bit you have eight
Exp bits, and you have 23 frack bits in double precision you have 11 the XP bits and
52 Fragments
now there's a number of different kinds of floating-point representations, the
Sort of the default and sort of the common representation is called normalized
so called normalized values and
normalized values are all the values where the Exp field is not equal to 0
And not equal not equal to all zeros and not equal to all ones okay, so everything all
Zeros and all ones are special kinds of numbers. We'll look at a second
so
the exponent
this exponent e remember our numbers are minus 1 to the power s
Times M times 2 raised to the Power E
the exponent e is
Encoded as this biased value
Which is the called exp?
so the x the exponent e is
Exp minus some bias and
Exp is the value
Capital Exp is the value of the Exp bits the bits in the Exp field treat it as a positive number
Ok so capital exp
is just you just look at it as an unsigned and
seven bit in case of single Precision Seven bit number
Okay, now the bias is
2 to the Power K minus 1 minus 1 where K is the number of exponent bits okay? So for single precision?
We have 8 exponent bits so 2 to the 8th 2 to the 8 minus 1 is 7 so 2 to the seventh is?
minus 1 is
127 okay, so the bias for single precision is 127 and
Similarly for double precision it's a thousand 23
okay, so you just
you just have to memorize this this formula the exponent e is
the Exp field
Interpret it as an unsigned number minus the the bias
now this is a
This is kind of a strange thing
The first time you encounter floating-point it. It seems kind of odd right. So why not I?
Mean we've already learned about two's complement
That's a perfectly fine way to represent positive and negative numbers okay, and we have exponents that are negative
And positive right so why not just use the Exp field to represent?
Or why not just use?
Two's complement in the Exp field to represent those positive and negative exponents right so it turns out that
The reason that they do this
is
That and if you think if I think about this and we'll come back to it
but if we if we encode the the exponent e
using this bias representation
The smallest negative exponent is represented by all zeros
okay, and the largest exponent is represented by
0 1 1 1 1
so the the smallest
the swamp the number with the smallest exponent
If we were just to compare the bits using it just some kind of unsigned
Representation just comparing the bits treating it as an unsigned number by using. This is this biased
Representation we can just compare two floating point numbers
Just as unsigned we can treat the whole floating point number as an unsigned integer and compare two numbers and get
Get a true comparison
So the exponent uses this this sort of biasing encoding and then the significance is encoded
with an implied one so and this is where the
This is where the normalized in the normalized representation comes from that
We're always going to represent our numbers so m
We're always going to normalize m no matter what the number we want to represent?
we're always going to normalize m as one point something and
Then we adjust the exponent accordingly right, so if if the value we want to represent is
one zero zero point zero one
We're going to shift it over and it'll be one point zero zero
Okay
And then we'll adjust the exponent to represent that shift
okay, so the
V bits in the Frac field xxxxx
are
All of the numbers to the right of the binary point right so there's always this implied one
But we don't even encode it. We just throw it away because it's always there all right
So this is a little trick just to get one more bit
for free
Okay, so the the xxx bits
in the fraks field
are all all of all the bits to the right of the binary point after one point the one point and this is the
so this is the smallest fractal is all zero's which Corresponds to a
significant of 1.0
And a fractal of all ones
Corresponds to two minus Epsilon, so that's one swing one long-run 1 1 and so on
So let's look at let's look at an example
So let's look at how we would encode
15 to 13 our favorite number
In two's complement and floating-point
So the if we represent that so it's an integer
And we represent it using
these fifths take my word for it correspond to
the integer 213
So now we want to convert it. We want to normalize it
by
Expressing it as one point 1 1 0 and so on times 2 to the 13th ok saying the same number
We just normalized it so that there's there's always this leading 1
So the significant M
is
1 point 1 1 0 1 1 and So on
the Frack Field is everything to the right of
the binary point so we just we throw this we throw this one away, and we just take the
the values to the right of the binary point and then we pat it out with zeros to to get the 23 bits that we
need for single precision
Okay, so now we've got our frack sealed
The exponent so in this case a yz
We're multiplying by 2 to the 13 so e is 13 so we want to represent the value 13 using this biased
encoding
So the bias is 127
and so the exponent the value that the value of the Exp field
should be 140 because if we take if we take 140
minus 127 we get
Okay, so 140 is represented using these eight bits and that becomes our Exp field
Okay, so the resulting floating-point number and of course. It's a positive number, so the sign Bill is zero
So the resulting floating point number has these eight the eight bits and Exp field that we computed by subtracting
140 by subtracting 127 from 140 and then
the Frack Field
Are these bits that we that we got here by just taking everything to the right of the binary point?
so this
So let's look at this exponent. Just a little bit more because I think can be a little confusing
so so in our example
if we want to look at the range of exp
So what's the smallest value of exp?
What's the smallest value of the Xp?
The way no no don't don't confuse the encoding with the value of represents
Exp is is just the encoding. So what's what's the smallest value of the xp?
0 that's right
Okay, and the largest value is is what remember?
It's what's the largest value yep?
Well the largest value would be remember it can't be all ones
Right so the largest value would be 2 to the 8th minus 1 so
Okay, so the largest value would be 0 1 1 1 1 0 followed by 7 ones
Ok, so that's a 2 to the 8th minus 1 is
255 good
Okay, so then what's the range then of the of e which is the actual value that we want to encode
Okay, remember use this we have this definition
So we have the range of values for Exp. We have our bias
So what are the range of values for it for e? This is the actual exponents that we're we're encoding
So what's the smallest exponent?
minus 127 good
right because that's
Zero is our smallest Exp minus the bias which is 127 okay, so the smallest value of e is is
it's 127 and the the largest value of e is
So if we take the largest value of Exp, that's 255 minus 127
okay, so the the
numbers that we can represent using this bias notation
will have the smallest exponent will be 2 to the minus 127 and
The largest exponent will be 2 to the raised to the power 128
Okay, so do you see
You see what's going on here. So we have
We have a range of values for e. Here's the largest value
Here's the smallest value here's 0 right in the middle these are the values we want to represent this biasing is like a shift
We've just now we're shifting up by 127 so that now the smallest exponent is
represented by 0
Okay, any questions about that
now
These normalized these normalized values always have this this implied one
okay, which
Which when we get clipped when we want to represent numbers closer to zero?
that limits us right, so there's another type of
floating-Point number called the de norm de normalized
value
which which is characterized by an Exp field of all zeros and
in a normal in a denormalized number or D norm there's no implied one, okay, so the the
significant m is
represented exactly is encoded identically in the in the frac field so there's no implied one and
all of the numbers are the form zero point
Something something something after them
in the exponent value E
Instead of remember for de norms we subtracted
Bias from Exp for D. Norms we subtract the bias from one?
okay, now you would just use the
The definition we use for normalized numbers that would be the Exp would be zero
So we don't do that instead, we?
Yi is 1 minus the bias and
Then the significant is coded with an implied leading zero instead of a leading one like I like I mentioned
so
so when Exp is zero and also I mean we
think about it if
If we only had denormalized numbers, we wouldn't be able to represent zero right because there's there'd always be a 1 in there
So the d norms allow us to represent zero and they only allow us to represent values that are very close to zero
so when the exponent is zero and
The Exp field is zero and the Frac field is zero then this is the zero value
And so this is nice because all zeroes represents zero which is you know sort of what what you want?
Now there is a sort of weird thing though that
If you have a sign, bit is
one and then your your Frakkin and an
Exp or zero then you have negative zero so you have this kind of odd situation where there's a positive and negative zero
Okay
and other values if the xp is zero, and you have a non zero frack then those are the
equally spaced numbers that are closest to zero
Now there's a couple of other special values when Exp is is
all one and
Frack is all zeros this represents the value infinity
so this is a value that that we get when
Is some kind of addition or multiplication and we overflow?
so in
Floating point always overflows to the special value called infinity the positive or negative infinity so it's different from two's complement rightward
You sort of overflowed and in this modular way
Back just back it around into the range of numbers in in floating point
We just overflow to the sticky value called infinity, and then then everything we do on that
remains infinity
so for example if we did a
if we did 1 divided by 0 or
We or minus 1 divided by minus 0 we get positive infinity if we divide
One by a zero negative zero we get negative infinity
the fourth the fourth kind of special case special number
Is the case where the exponent again is all once but the frac is is Nonzero
in a non zero value
And this represents what's called not a number, so this is
This is this this lift handles cases with where there's no. There's no answer
There's no feasible answer for example if we you know try to take the square root of -1
What we'll get back is not a number
So 2 I think it's helpful to to visualize these
the number line now, so the
We have positive zero negative zero sort of right next to each other and then to
The right of that are the positive D norms?
and then those then those sort of
Transition into the
normalized numbers
And then you have infinity
Positive infinity they have a similar
similar situation on the for the negative numbers and then negative and positive nodded numbers
so I think the you know he's probably you've probably discovered now that a
Really good way to try to understand these
American coatings, it's just to do examples with only a few numbers bits. You know if you want to understand like for example in tooth
If you want to understand t min and t max and and how they relate to each other just do a three bit
Two's complement system. You know imagine just have a system with two's complement of three bits
and then you can just enumerate all those all the
possibilities, and you can see
And then you see where you know the t min is actually
One greater than t max you know so if you add one to t max it actually overflows into t min
maybe a
Similar thing for floating-point. It's I would really encourage you to do this just try some simple examples with a
sort of Tyent with a small number of Exp and frac bits so in this case, we're going to look at A
floating-point system based on I triple e that has for Exp bits and three fraC bits
As always the sign bit, it's the most significant bit
followed by Exp followed by Frac
Okay, so this is this is identical to I triple e floating point except for the size of that
Exp in fractions
So it's actually small enough that we can now just enumerate
these values and
And now you can I?
You can start to see why these weird
definitions for the exponent in donora and normalized numbers, so let's just look at
So what we've done here. We've just with a signed bit of zero. We've we've just enumerated
all of the two to the seventh
possibilities possible
combinations of Exp and Frac Fields starting with zero
okay, so when when exp is all zeros, that's a d norm right by definition and
then we have
the three FraC bits or all zero
okay, so remember the Exp is all zeros right so the four D norms the
The exponent value is 1 minus the bias our bias here is seven
Okay, so one minus seven gives us a value for the exponent of minus six
So we're going to take the frac
the bits in the in the in the frac field
times
so m is zero
So m in this case is zero
times
2 to the minus 6 gives us zero, okay?
So this this is our reference state representation of zero and like I said it's really
It's nice that it actually is if we just treated this as an unsigned
Integer we just it
Would be zero okay, so that's kind of pleasing
Now let's look at the very next number right the x exp is still zero and we've just bumped up
Track by one
Okay, so again it's it's a one minus the bias which is
minus six
And now this this frack
field represents
This is 1/2
1/4
1/8 so it represents, so this is a value of Amaz it is 1/8
So 1/8
Times 2 to the minus 6 which is 1
64th equals 1 over 512 so in this floating point system the smallest Nonzero number we can represent is the
denormalized representation of 1 over 512
the next smallest number is 0
okay, now let's look at so let's take let's bump this up by 1 so now we get a
We get a fraC sealed of 0 1 0 so this represents
1/4
So e/m is 1/4 that significant is 1/4 times
2 to the Minus 6 So 2 8
Times 1 64 is 2 to the 5 12?
okay, so
the the numbers were just
Invite by incrementing this by incrementing
Armored-Car significant, we're increasing the numbers by
1 over 512
now the largest d norm in this number system is the case where the frack field is all ones and
so this encodes
1/2
Plus 1/4 Plus 1/8
which is 7/8 and
then our value is
7/8 times
2 to the minus 6 or 1 over 64 and that equals 7 512
so this
7 over 512 is the largest denormalized number we can represent in this system
and now if we if we bump our number up by one
the
The Frac field resets to zero and now the Exp field goes from zero to one
Now because the Exp field is non-0 this this is no longer a denormalized number. It's a normalized number
okay, so now we're changing the
Definition of e from 1 minus the bias to Exp minus the bias
So what's what's Exp in this case?
Minus 7 the bias is minus 6 so Lo and Behold
it's the same it's the same it's
the same
exponent as the previous denormalized number
So this is this is actually very clever by the I triple e folks
because you get the spirit you get this nice smooth transition from de norms to norms to normalize, so
You can see that
Our our exponent. E is minus 6 still and now our
Because we're taking 1 minus the bias 7 and our signature
Significant now remember this is a normalized number because the Exp field is Nonzero
Just this the a fraction of all zeros represents a significant of one point zero zero zero
Okay, so this this normalized number this the smallest normalized number
Represents is one point zero zero zero which is 8 8 times
2 to the Minus 6 which is 1 over 64
Which gives us 8 over 512 so if we've made this nice smooth transition from 7 over 5 12 to 8 over 512?
And I'll do one more. I don't want to be
so if we bump if
We bump keeping the Exp field at 1 if we bump our fracks deals from 0 to 1
now this represents the the
significant of 1
point 0
one point zero zero one
Which is eight eight plus one eight?
So that's nine eight
times and then the value is
Nine eight times 2 to the minus six once 1 over 64 which is equal to 9 over 512 okay?
Any questions about that?
question back here
Okay, the question is why is why do you choose to bias that to be 2 to the K minus 1 minus 1 well go?
Back to my my singer diagram here, so this is the range of the Xp fields that you want to
This is the range of e that you want to represent with 0 in the middle
Okay, and so you want to bias it so that this is halfway 0 the smallest exponent
Is Halfway to 0?
So you want the bias to shift it up, so it's the smallest
The smallest encoded the smallest value of Exp Corresponds to the smallest exponent
Right so 2 to the K minus 1 minus 1 is just giving you it's giving you a value. That's halfway
between the smallest exponent and the largest exponent
Okay
That's good any other questions
okay, if we take a like a little smaller six bit format same thing as we did before just different numbers of
Bits and Exp and frac, and then we plot these on the number line you can see that
you can see that the values are very dense around zero, so they're very spaced very closely together and
Then every time you increase the exponent by one
the numbers are spaced twice
twice as far apart as the previous the number the numbers that
Are represented by the previous exponent?
So you can see like in this little example
You see these
These values here are all equally spaced
Now these these four values are equally spaced
And they're right next to each other and then you
See this jump in the spacing that represents an increase in the Exp field by one
And then it and then that spacing doubles as we go out
And you can see it. You can see it even better here. This if we if we zoom in
These blue values are the are
these blue values or D norms and
then we have
The the next set of normalized values where the frack field is one. They're spaced the same, right?
We saw this when we kept increasing by by one over 512
And then we increase the the exponent by one and the spacing doubles
okay, so this like I mentioned this this encoding has some some pretty nice properties the
The floating point zero zero zero is encoded as integers here. Which is nice
and with the exception of
Not a number
With the exception of not a number you can compare any floating-point numbers?
Including infinity by just treating it as doing an unsigned
Comparison so that's that's really nice, too
Now if you when you add and multiply floating point numbers right we're dealing with a limited set of bits here
so if we take if we take two numbers
Encoded as floating-point, and we add them together. There's there's no guarantee that we'll be able to fit all those bits in the bits
we have available to us the
There's no guarantee that we'll be able to fit the bits and the result
So what?
So what we do in this case is you can imagine?
The Model You want to have with floating point operations addition to multiplication is
That you you add or multiply you do the addition or multiplication and you compute the exact result you
just assume that you have an infinite amount of number of bits and
then you round use the technique called rounding to get it to fit into the of
The available bits okay, so the effect is like you're doing say x plus y is
getting the precise value
of x plus y at an infinite number of bits and then rounding into the
available bits
So let's look at this this idea of rounding it this can be confusing the first time you see it it requires
You need to think about it carefully
To get it right now in I triple e. There's four different kinds of rounding
There's round towards zero round down route or round to minus infinity
round up to
Which is rounding it to positive infinity and then the default case which is the only one really we're really going to consider which is
round to the nearest even
And this is what I triple e does by default
You can you can if you go into assembly language you can change the rounding, but we're not going to consider it any more
yes question
the
I'm sorry
There is right because there's one so the question is there a distinct
negative infinity and a distinct positive infinity
And there is they have the exact same bit representation except the most significant bit for negative infinity is one
And for positive infinity at zero
yes question
White is nearest even oh, I'll show you let me go over the others the question was about nearest even yes
Greater than big well. That was me that was the exception right today. That's right so so aside from
Infinity, you can't do that comparison
positive infinity works
Right, but not negative, so you're right. That's good point
All right, so let's look at these rounding modes, and I'll explain
Live at the Neuro Steven works, but let's look at so rounding towards zero what we're going to do
We'll use dollars so we want to round to the nearest dollar
Towards Zero just anything less than
You just around
You just round towards zero so dollar forty would go to one a dollar sixty would go down to one a dollar fifty to one
To fifty would go to two
Negative 150 you round toward zero so that would be negative negative one
round down Towards negative infinity
It's similar the only difference is that for negative one point?
Negative a dollar fifty you'd round towards negative
Infinity which would be minus two
rounding up is the
is
symmetric to round down the interesting case is
round to nearest even
Interesting because it's what I triple e floating point actually uses so the idea here
If you if you have a value that's less than half
Then you round down if you have a value that's more than halfway between two dollar amounts you round up
the route that nearest even part comes when you have
Something that's exactly halfway
Then what you do is you round towards the nearest even number
Okay, so in in this example a dollar forty because it's less than it's less than half
rounds down to one dollar a dollar sixty is greater than half so we round up to two dollars a
dollar Fifty right in the Middle
We round
Round up to the nearest even knock dollar amount. Which is two dollars
two dollars and fifty
Cents we round down to the nearest even right if we round it up. It would be three which is a oDd number and
- a dollar fifty we round - we
Round down to minus - two dollars
So the reason we do this the reason they chose. This is that
statistically if
You would imagine if you have a uniform distribution of sort of numbers
They're going to round up or down about 50 percent of the time, so there won't be a statistical bias
Rounding up or down one way or the other okay? So that's the that's the reason they did that
now
You can apply this you can do this rounding to any
to any any any value, so in the last example, we did it to
The nearest dollar but let's suppose. We wanted to round to the nearest hundredth using round two even
the default round - even mode
So we want to round
to the nearest
Hundredth is the second position this first do we have tenths and hundredths
So if we have a value seven point eight nine for $9.99 that's less than halfway
Halfway would be
Any number that had a five followed by all zeros
So for 999 is less than that
So we would just round down to 7.89
Even though 9 is odd. The only the only time we're going to apply round 2 even is when we're exactly halfway
Okay, our next the next example seven point eight nine five zero zero one that's greater than halfway
Right if this if this was a zero it would be exactly halfway, so we round up to seven point nine
Okay, now here's the interesting case where we have seven point eight nine five
Followed by all zeroes that's exactly halfway. So now we now we apply the round to nearest even rule
Eight nine is the negative an odd number so that doesn't work so we round up and we do that basically by adding
adding a 5 here, so
5 + 5 is 10 and then that carries over
God
to the next position and 9 + 1 is 0
9 + 1 is 10 so that carries over and so 8 + 8 + 1 is 9 so the result is set of rounds
ero
Okay, is that clear you see?
It's a very mechanical way when you round up. It's always it's a very mechanical like that. You always just add
the half way number in this Case 5 and
Then just just propagate it out just do the addition and that will give you the nearest
The nearest that will round you up to the nearest
hundredth in this case
Okay, now the last case seven point eight eight five
Followed by all zeroes that's that's another number. That's halfway between
between two numbers
Rounded to the nearest hundredth so in this case
eight is
Even so we just we round down and to round down. We just truncate just throw these bits
These these digits away, and we get seven point eight eight
So there any questions about this
question back here yep
yep, that's the question was if
numbers that have the same
Exp field
Will will those numbers be equally spaced on the number line and the answer is yes?
yes question
all
Right and things done. Thank you in the last example Deltas. Why'd you run it would round up?
Yeah, the only
The half way values are always in this case because it's Base 10
the the half way number in Base 10 is 5 and
Then so it's always the half way number in this case 5 followed by all zeros
You always have that the half way if a value is halfway between like 200 it'll always have that that form
All right now. We can do the same thing with with binary fractional numbers as well
now a binary number is is even if it if the
least significant digit is 0
Ok we only have two digits right so odd is 1 and 0 is even
Ok and the halfway so the halfway
value is going to be a
1 followed by all zeros ok that represents exactly halfway ok so it's very it's analogous
analogous to the Base 10 example
Except where the halfway value is going to be 1 followed by all zeros
so let's look let's look at some examples, so
Suppose we have we want to represent two
and three thirty-seconds and
Suppose we only have four bits to do that in
Okay, well to represent that exactly
we need
seven bits
And so we have to round okay?
so let's look at
So we're going to round to
this two bits right at the binary point and
So let's look at all the bits that follow that
so since it starts with zero
This is going to be less than halfway
So since it's less than halfway we just truncate just chop those out and the result is
10.00
Now our next example is one zero point zero zero one one zero, so if we look at these
the bits to the right of these
to the right of the the bit we're rounding to
Since it starts with one, and it's not followed by all zeros that's greater than half okay
so
For the in this case we have to round up and so the way we do that is
we take we take one and we add it to this leftmost one right here and just
Do the addition and the result is one zero point zero one
Now let's look at two to the seven eight
This is represented as one zero point one one one zero zero
Now here's that here's that half way marker that we were looking for
it's a 1 followed by all zeros, so this is exactly half way, so now we have to round to the nearest even
number now
That if we can't just truncate because then it would be an odd number right we would end
10.11 is an oDd number
So we have to round up
And we do that by adding
we do that by adding a 1
Right here to this less leftmost red, bit. We add one to that and then just do the addition and we end up with
11.00
Which is three so the nearest?
The nearest value to two to the seventh eighth
The nearest rounded value is three
okay, our last example two to the five a's
We have the same
Halfway marker again one zero zero
But in this case the the hundreds bit are the one fourth bit is
Zero so that's even so we can just truncate we just throw those bits away, and the result is simply
10.10
That makes sense
so it's very mechanical and
mainly you just need to be able to recognize that halfway Marker and
Then figure out if you need to round up or down if you're going to round down just truncate you're going to round up add
A one and just propagate it
to get your result
Okay
Now we won't spend much time. I just want to mention a few things about multiplication in addition
so if we if we multiply two numbers, so we have different mantises significance and exponents and
suppose that the result is
M times two to the E
The sign bit will be the xor of the two sign bits of the two operands
the significant M will be
the multiplying M1 times M2 and the exponents are added right because
They're just by the rules of exponents
so if m is
If m is greater than 2 and this is a normalized number we have to
We have to we have to shift it and we have to
Put it in the range between 1 and 2 by shifting to the right and incrementing the exponent
if he's out of range, then we overflow 2
to infinity
and
Then if if m has too many bits, we have to use round 2 even to fit it into the available of fragments
Okay, addition. So suppose. We're trying to add two floating point numbers
Conceptually what you do is think of think of those numbers as fractional binary numbers you want to line up the binary points?
line up the Binary points then do the addition and then
a and then do the addition and that if
and then normalize the number so that the normalized the significance of it's between 1 & 2
and
either do that by shifting shifting right or left if he's too big then you overflow and then you round the
the bits and m to fit into the available for x field
now remember when we the first day of class we we talked about we call these great realities that Intz aren't really integers and
Floats aren't really reals
So the and just as just as just as we saw when we looked at
Two's complement representation of integers, it's not exactly
They're not exact exactly like real integers and operations on them aren't exactly like real integers
But they follow very predictable mathematical properties, okay that are similar to
Integers, but not quite so the same thing holds for floating-point numbers
They follow very
predictable
they have very predictable mathematical properties, but there's
somewhat different from the reals and the the big thing is
Is that the big big thing with addition is that it doesn't associate?
ok it's it's commutative, but it's not associative and
This usually happens when you have who you're dealing with numbers that have very large
dynamic ranges so a big if you're trying to add and subtract really big numbers with
It really little numbers you run into this this problem with non associativity
So the the example was if we take three point one four
plus two to the tenth
Two to the tensest so there's so much larger than three point one four
that when we
The bits that would be two to the tenth plus three the point one four the the bits that represent the three point one four
You know there's bits way out here that represent
There's one bit out here that represents two to the tenth, and then there's a few bits here they represent
Three point one four and there's just not enough
We don't have enough bits to represent all those so we have the three point one. Four goes goes away, so adding a
big number to a little number
Essentially gives the big number and then if you said you subtract that big number you get zero
now if
We change the the associate of the association
if we take this big number and subtract it from itself we get zero and then
So the result will be instead of zeros before we get three point one four
So other than that you you have all of the things that you would normally expect
Closed under addition. It's commutative. There's a additive identity of zero
Except for infinities, and nan's there's there's an additive inverse that you can take for any number
There's there's an inverse that will give you zero when you add it together
And you get monotonicity?
monotonicity between between values except of course for infinities and ends now multiplication has
Some it's similar you get it's closed generally under multiplication. It's commutative, but
It's not associative, and it doesn't distribute over addition
And it's the same so here you can see we're taking two to xx x - 2 xx
x - 2 xx and that gives infinity
But if we if we reassociate, and we take I'm sorry
To to the 20 times 2 to the 20th times 2 to the minus 20th
well this first multiplication is infinity and anything anything you do with infinity is just
Infinity, so the result is infinity
however if We associate and
multiply to xx times 2 to the minus 20th
that gives us 1 and then x
2 to the 20th until we get 2 to the 20th, so the big Takeaway point here is that?
A
floating point
floating point is an associative ok
Now is that a problem
It's something you have to be aware of and but generally I mean I
I've done a lot of scientific computing in particular
modeling
earthquake ground motion in Southern California
so basically we would we would build models of Southern California in the computer, and then we would shake them and
Then we would see how the ground moves in like Los Angeles
and those that that's shaking we used a
Numerical method called finite Elements, and it was all used all floating points single precision floating point numbers
And we never ran into a problem this with this associativity right? We would do we would do operations in different orders
we couldn't always guarantee that we would do the operations in the exact same order, but we never ran into a problem with this because
nature and generally in General is kind of smooth right that
if you look at the
You know if one part of the ground is shaking like this
And you look at the next part it might be shaking a little more or a little less
But you're not going to have like huge differences
And so we never ran into those kind of problems
but in some so if generally if you if you're simulating natural phenomena
You don't often see these kind of huge dynamic ranges, but other times. You know if it's not
Non natural financial maybe financial systems they use floating point
Then you might see this larger dynamic the numbers, and it might might become a problem
So as a programmer you just generally have to be aware of this you have to have a good
sense for the dynamic range of your numbers, and you have to keep in mind that if you if you reassociate
Or change the order of things
You may not get exactly the same
Exactly the same answer
okay, so C gives us two different kinds of
Floating points, so they the float is the I triple e single precision and double is the I triple e double precision?
now you remember when we did casting between
Intz and unsigned values back and Forth the cast never changed the bit representation it just changed the way that in
fact it never even changed the
the
the what the how the Alu
Manipulated those bits. It's really just a how we're interpreting and how we're viewing those those values however when you do cast between
floats and
Intz and doubles the bit representation changes right so a cast here has a
Dramatic effect on the actual bits themselves now if we go from a double or a float
to an int
it's going to it's just going to it's going to truncate the fractional part and give us the
Give us the the integer part and then and then round to fit oh
Actually, no there won't be
Okay, so think about this how many there were she said 23
23 Frack bits and float and I
Forget exactly how many in doubles anybody remember it doesn't matter it's um it's some number
Well, no, it doesn't matter looks
so for a float if we if we cast a float to an int
We're casting 23 something that we can represent
with 23
at most 23 frack bits
into A
32 bit int so we won't we'll never lose so we won't we'll never need to do any rounding
but double-Precision
has 52 bits
okay, so they're there we may not be able to fit the the
represented integer into the into the end so they'll
They'll have to be some rounding
sorry Powerpoint crashed
Okay
Right now if we cast if we cast from an int to a double
There's will have will have enough debt so we won't lose anything, right?
the 32 bits
will fit in the double precision Frac field and
but int to float
Has there's more there's more bits than an int that then there are in the frac field will float
So we'll have to do some rounding right so the so casting works the same way as any other operation
you can think of it as just taking the
Assume you have an infinite number of bits get the exact result and then round it to fit into the available disk
All right, so let's the final thing. I want to do today is
sort of test your understanding
Do solve some puzzles to test test to understanding of these?
properties of floating-Point numbers
So imagine that we have three values acts as an int f is a float and d is a double
and then we're evaluating the CC expressions so x
Is x equal to int float x yeah?
How you can edit out the you can edit out that other stuff?
All right, so what do you think if we?
So if we take x which is an int
cast it to a float and
then cast that back to an int will that always be equal to x
No, make as we lose some bits right? We don't have enough breakfast in float
what about if we take x cast it to a double and
Then cast it back to ant well. We always get
equivalent value, yeah
Because we have enough practice and in double
Now what if we take a float f?
Cast it to a double and then cast it back to a float well that always equal the original f
Yeah
What about the converse though? What if we take the double d cast it to a float can cast it back to a double no?
How about this how about if we take f?
Negate it and then negate that again will that always equal f?
Yeah, because we're just toggling a bit right soon
Okay, how about?
Two over three equal two over three point. Oh
no, because 2 over 3 is 0
and 2
Over 3.0 is a is a floating point value
2/3 the floating point representation of 2/3 okay. How about if if the double d is less than 0?
Does that imply that d times 2 is also less than 0?
Yeah
even if no matter what even if even if 2 times d overflows it will overflow to
negative infinity which is less than
Which is less than 0?
Okay, how about does the double d greater than f imply that minus f is greater than minus D?
Yeah, that's that monotonicity right and again. It's just yes
- with people euros and float that both are double
Oh, that's a good question. I think it'd be explode I
Think if we if you put there's an annotation in situ to give it a double, but actually I'd have to check that out. That's
Enough yeah, that's a good question. I don't know
We'd have to check off to go and look in the in the see guide
How about it is D squared the double D squared always greater than or equal to zero?
Yes
And how about the D plus f minus d always equal f now because of lack of associativity?
Okay
So that was that was that was fun right the floating points always fun
So anyway that the big thing is just to realize that
floats aren't exactly really reals, but they have very
predictable property and
that
They're not associative or commutative. They're not associative and
So you have to be careful about that?
All right, we'll have a good weekend. We'll see you on Tuesday